Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin 1787-1790 Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning his affair with Mr. Thomas.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Anderson, John. Glasgow College
    Forwarding Franklin his "Institutes of Physics," which may be of use to some young lecturer in Philadelphia; sends with it Sir John Dalrymple's "Memoirs," [of Great Britain and Ireland], volume two; reviews this work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Pagin, Pére. Paris
    Recalls the pleasant hours spent together at Madame Brillon's, M. and Mme. Le Veillard's and other friends. Reminds him of his promise on behalf of his nephew, M. Milliet, to whom M. Dorhman owes a considerable sum of money; encloses a memoir with an account of the affair, also an open letter from his nephew to M. Dorhman.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Transmits the account. French politics; strenuous struggle by the Parliaments to fix the prerogatives of the Crown; refusal of the Bordeaux Parliament to hold their meetings in the small inland town to which they have been ordered; possibility of a great change in the Constitutions of France. Commercial relations between France and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Anderson, John. Glasgow College
    Sending him two books with a long explanatory letter in each one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. Golden Square, London
    Sending this letter by the American Ministers, Mr. [John] Adams and Col. Smith; they are not the bearers of any Treaty of Amity and Commerce; hopes for better feeling in the future; wishes America peace and prosperity under her new Constitution. Compares England to old wine in old bottles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, Charles. Boston
    The papers of Dr. Ingen Housz in Mr. [John] Williams's possession. Interest on certain moneys. Account of the Conventions [to ratify the Constitution] in New Hampshire, Massachusetts and Rhode Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Wedgwood, Josiah. London
    Sending a few cameos for the use of Franklin and his friends; the subject of them the abolition of slavery; delighted to be embarked with Franklin in the same great and good cause. Owing to a continuous headache, is obliged to make use of his nephew's hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Phillips, James. London
    Books he is sending to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Picque, -----. Pittsburg
    As they are about to leave Fort Pitt, begs Franklin to hold their letters until their destination is assured.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Maskelyne, Nevil. Greenwich
    Concerning Churchman's theory of the variation of the magnetic needle; opinion of the Board of Longitude unfavorable; their reasons. Hopes the [American] Philosophical Society received his Greenwich Observations.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 462; Bigelow, IX, 571).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Whatley, George. London
    His attitude concerning the abolition of the slave-trade; does not agree with the Society in all its tenets. News of Dr. [William] Rowley; works to serve the public not to gain money. Refuses to believe in the report of Franklin's death.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Obliged for his opinion concerning the steam-boat; trusts the encouragement Mr. [John] Fitch hopes from Congress, will enable him to cheapen, simplify and render his machine still more useful; should he succeed in perfecting it, he will deserve the applause of America and Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Guillotin, Joseph Ignace
    Begs for a reply to his questions concerning America; entreats the continuance of his kindness and protection towards Messrs. Picque and Saugrain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Thomas, Isaiah. Worcester Mass
    Presenting Franklin with a copy of his edition of Perry's Dictionaries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, John
    Good reports of Franklin's health; sees his handwriting has undergone no alteration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Whatley, George. London
    Wrote on the 1st inst. principally to ascertain the chances of his friend Dashwood receiving the money due him from Mr. George Henry of Philadelphia. Has finally heard from Mr. Jonathan Williams [Jr.]; the sin of procrastination. At Dr. [William] Rowley's request, sends one of his late publications on a malady, the treatment of which he considers improper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 March 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Concerning two small boxes sent to Franklin, one containing the Philosophical Transactions from the Royal Society, the other De Luc's Hygrometer, a present from Mr. [ Edward] Nairnc. Urges Franklin to collect in book form many of his useful little papers that apply to common conduct in life for the lower and middle classes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 1; A.L.S. 5p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    The result of the great [Constitutional] Convention in America; objects to certain points; thinks the power of the President too great. News of friends at Passy. His election as Syndic of his town; if his position is not so brilliant as Franklin's, is surrounded by more charming women. Entreats him to hasten the writing of his memories; false and stupid anccdotes written about him by Baron de Trink and others. Concerning imposts and duties. Critical and alarming condition of affairs in France; financial situation deplorable. With the exception of his wife, cares more for Franklin than anyone else in the world; why he cannot gratify his desire to go to Philadelphia. M. [Jacques] Necker's work on the importance of religious convictions. Death of [George Louis Le Clerc, Comte] du Buffon; his successor, [Comte Charles Claude La]billarderie [D'Angiviller].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Caslon, William. London
    News in his family. Messages to his friend, W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Pownall, Thomas. Bristol
    Report of Franklin's death. Is the only Commissioner left of those representing and acting for the several Provinces in America, who met at the Congress in Albany in 1754. Political condition of the Swiss Cantons. Constitution of the United States; fears the result of a four years' term for the President.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 342).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Coxe, Tench
    Glad to see that the people abroad look with desire at America, in spite of the disordered situation of commerce and Government. Will take a few days to turn over in his mind the letter enclosed to him by Franklin; will then ask his attention to one or two points.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Flamstead, Jamaica
    Concerning the Island of Jamica; the cause of mortality among the soldiers; condition of the slaves far better than that of the poor in several parts of Europe; if there is to be a reform, it must be of slow growth; this applies also to conditions in the Southern States; believes however that white men can labor equally well in the cultivation of sugar, etc. Facts determined by the thermometer and hygrometer. Meteorological observations he has made which point out other laws than those in Franklin's ingenious theory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Millon, J.C. Au Cap François
    Introducing M. de Moret, who goes to America for his health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Turner, G. Philadelphia
    Directed by Gen. [Henry] Knox at the last General Meeting of the Cincinnati, to translate and return to Franklin the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 April 30; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gilpin, Joseph
    Sending him samples of such kinds of paper as have been made at the Brandywine manufactory; his uncle, Mr. Fisher, desires the loan of those books on the subject of paper-making which Franklin was good enough to offer him yesterday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Boxes sent to Franklin; one containing De Lue's Hygrometer. His mother's health much better. Dr. [Joseph] Priestley well and busy. Dr. [Richard] Price engaged in calculations respecting poor laws and rates for the House of Commons. Mr. [Thomas] Gilbert's bill thrown out.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Pemberton, James. Philadelphia
    Meeting of the Society [for the Abolition of the Slave-trade] called; [the Wedgwood] cameos mostly distributed; suggests sending a few of the pamphlets also. The ship which fitted out the previous summer for the nefarious business to Africa is reported to be refitting at some port in Delaware; their intention to notify the Governor as well as the Abolition Society in Wilmington that, if practicable, the attempt may be frustrated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Davis, William. Boston
    Hopes that among the large circle of his Excellency's friends, some relief may be afforded him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Introducing the Rev. Mr. [Timothy] Hilliard and Mr. Thomas Lee, both of Cambridge, Mass.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Introducing Christopher Gore, Esq., a lawyer of note, and a warm advocate of federalism and of the proposed Federal Constitution; favorable prospect of its adoption in New Hampshire; already adopted by Maryland; trusts the complete adoption of it is not far distant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Lathrop, Dr. John
    Introducing the Rev. Mr. [Timothy] Hilliard, who succeeds the venerable Dr. [Nathaniel] Appleton to the ministry at Cambridge; his travelling companion is Thomas Lee, Esq., a wealthy retired merchant. Feels himself acquainted with Franklin on account of his friendship with Mrs. [Jane] Mecom. Sends him the last publication of their Humane Society; thinks the world improves.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Wallace and Muir. Annapolis
    Sending the enclosed letter by Mr. E. Lawrence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Smallwood, W. Annapolis
    Desiring Franklin to authorize the delivery to Samuel Swan, of one William Clelone, committed to jail in Philadelphia, charged with stealing a horse and saddle; necessary that he should be tried in Maryland for this and other offenses against the state. Instructions to Samuel Swan. [2 p.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gore, Christopher. Philadelphia
    An unexpected call from the city prevents his dining with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Thevenard, Comte Antoine Jean Marie. L'Orient
    Acknowledging the present of his "Maritime Observations"; solaces himself for Frankliln's absence by regarding his portrait.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 May 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Coxe, Tench
    Transmitting the enclosed papers for Franklin's approbation and signature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Soderstrom, Richard. New York
    Introducing Messrs. John and [Sir] Alexander [Forrester] Cochrane.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Hillegas, Michael. New York
    Introducing Captain and Mr. Cochrane, both brothers of Lord Dundonald; belives all three carry on the famous coal and tar works in divers parts of England and Scotland; the great effects produced and experienced from the use of their tar, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Kemp, Fr. Adr. Van der
    Is the bearer of a letter from the Marquis de la Fayette. Intends making a tour through the country with a view to finding a convenient settlement for himself and family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Carey, Mathew. Philadelphia
    Hopes the unhappy misunderstanding over the types purchased from Franklin will not prevent Franklin from doing him a favor; his plan to increase the subscribers to the American Museum published by himself; suggests a highly laudatory description of the American Museum which he wishes Franklin to write for him and sign.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 16; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Powel, Mrs
    Begging the loan of Franklin's sedan-chair for a Virginia gentleman, who is laboring under such severe and weakening complaints, as to render him incapable of being moved in a wheel-carriage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 25; L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Inclosed the report of Council authorizing him to purchase the land adjoining the northern boundary of the State.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Armbruster, Anthony. Germantown
    Begging for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Mestre, Etienne. Bordeaux
    Concerning certain casks of wine shipped to Franklin by order of M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Meyen,Johann Jacob Ph.D. Alt-Stetrin on the Oder, Pommerania
    An eulogy on Dr. Franklin as Philosopher, Statesman and Patriot.
    (In German.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Non-arrival of the second volume of the [American] Philosophical [Society's] Transactions sent to their Society; enclosed Mr. [Caleb] Gannett's letter on the subject [XXXVI, 63]; trusts the French work which Franklin has left them in his will, may be long out of their possession. Franklin's expectation of retiring from public cares. Pleasure derived from reading his ingenious queries concerning magnetism and the theory of the Earth; pleasant speculations to which they give rise. Introducing Mr. John Stewart, a grandson of the late Capt. Erving.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 June 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Carles, L. St. Nicolas
    His misfortunes increased; begs for a letter of recommendation to M. [Barbé] de Marbois, who may procure him a position which will enable his family to live. Sent him two engravings of the Loge des Commandeurs de Carcassonne in December, 1787.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Guillotin, Joseph Ignace
    Overwhelmed with horror at the news of the massarce by Indians of the party from Pittsburg; doubts not that the French botanist and mineralogist mentioned are his two young friends; report that one of them, though severely wounded, escaped; begs for further news; such a tragedy would cause the complete abandonment of the proposed settlement; if both men are alive, begs that they may be given every care and assistance; will send the necessary funds.
    (In duplicate. In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Wallace and Muir. Annapolis
    Sending the enclosed by a safe hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 8; A.L. 2P.; Condorcet, marquis de
    Acknowledging his election to the [American] Philosophical Society. The new Federal Constitution of the United States; if nothing better could be obtained, looks upon it as a necessary evil. Affairs in France; clamors against despotism; dread of civil war or bankruptey.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 353; Bigelow, X, 1).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Thomas, -----. Paris
    His affair with Messrs. Bache and Shee; acknowledging Franklin's reply with the bill of sale, asked for so often in vain; cannot regard the business as ended, since the balance due him has never been paid; relies on Franklin's good offices to receive prompt payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 12; A.L.S. 7p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis-Alexandre duc de La Roche-Guyon et de. Varennes
    Memoirs of Franklin's life. The new Federal Constitution; extent of the power granted the President; confidence implied in Washington and his successors. Political condition of France; States-General demanded by the public; faults in the form of this body; preference for a National Assembly; fears for these first steps in the career of liberty; America's position far more favorable for the establishment of a good Constitution. Sending him a disscrtation on Nyctalopia, a disease endemic in the neighborhood of La Rocheguyon.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 354; Bigelow, X, 2).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Clos, Beruin. New York
    If he had a fraction of the talents of the celebrated Abbé Raynal, would erect to Franklin a monument as lasting as his name. Condemns the base mutilation of William Pitt's statue at New York, Revolution of the last ten years; America has broken her chains and Holland has embraced hers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Rush, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Enclosing an extract from Dr. [David] Ramsay's intended history of the Revolution; with the author's request for any corrections in the facts which Frankliln deems neccessary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; St. Trys, -----. Boston
    At the request of Mr. [Thomas] Paine, sends Franklin the report of the French Academy of Sciences on his iron bridge.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 July 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Despeintreaux, Lucas
    His purchase of a small plantation six miles from Pittsburg where he is at present living in great content; expects a sum of money to arrive from France for him; begs Franklin to take charge of it and have it forwarded by a safe conveyance; M. Saugrain [de Vigny] has promised to see that it is sent to Franklin's care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Eyes, George White. Princeton
    Has only one more year to finish his college course; begs Franklin, as a great friend of his mother, to send him a small sum of money and the articles of clothing mentioned; promises to repay the loan in money or land.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Oswald, Elizabeth. Philadelphia
    Begs him to consider her husband's case and give her his opinion; sure he will agree with her that Mr. [Eleazer] Oswald has been unjustly confined.
    A.E. by Frankliln. As he may be called on to judge her husband's case officially, cannot give her his present sentiments thereon; wishes that her prudent counsels might cause him to change the conduct of his paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Stewart, Mary. London
    Sent him twelve copies of her brother's work; account of various misfortunes experienced since she last saw Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Introducing M. [Brissot] de Warville and his fellow-traveller, Col. de La Terrière.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Fisher, Miers. Philadelphia
    Returning with thanks, the two volumes of the Transactions of the French Academy; remarks concerning the memoirs on paper manufactures. Sends a ream of paper lately manufactured at Brandywine Mills; thinks it an improvement on the last.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Martin, William. Philadelphia
    Observations on paper-money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Jennings, Samuel. London
    Mr. [Benjamin] West's kindness to him; has forwarded four pictures for him; is at present on the fifth-St. Paul shaking the viper from his hand, intended for the chapel at Greenwich. Exciting election in Westminister.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    His arrival in Paris; saw Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson, who drew up the power of attorney which will enable Mr. [Samuel] Vaughan [Jr.] to act for him in his affair with Mr. [Samuel] Wharton. Accepts the advice to hold his Certificates of Congress until the new Government is established; question of buying land with the money. Franklin's pointed remarks on the Turkish war. Dined with Mr. [John] Paradise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Rumsey, James. London
    Money to be made if he had the privilege of erecting boats to go by steam; possibility of forming a connection with Messrs. Bolton and Watt; his boiler much improved; favorable opinion expressed by all who have seen it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Sauris, St. Marc de
    His desire to obtain the Order of Cincinnatus; states his services under the Comte de Grasse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 26; L.S. 3p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    The new Constitution given to America; part played by Franklin and Washington in this great work; sends him her felicitations; hopes his life will be as famous for its length as for its talents and virtues; quotes the verses she recited in his honor at the small entertainment at Sannois.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Kemp, Fr Adr Van der. New York
    Acknowledging Franklin's polite reception of him in Philadelphia. Has purchased a valuable farm two miles from Esopus in New York State.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 August 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Nancarrow, John. Pittsburgh
    Assisted a great many Americans confined in Mill prison during the war. Account of his business ventures and final emigration to America with his family; heavy money losses; his intention of moving to Lexington, Kentucky; probability of a post-office being established there; begs Franklin's influence to obtain him the position of post-master.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 September 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Hillegas, Michael. New York
    Money borrowed from Mr. James Hamilton; security he gave him; transfer of the sum to Messrs. Howell and Emlen, to whom the security was also assigned; these gentlemen anxious to receive the interest and principle; understands Franklin puts out money at interest; begs him to furnish the amount due these gentlemen and promises the best security and prompt payment of interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 September 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Nicholson, Jno. Philadelphia
    Laying before Franklin a plan for removing the present embarrassments occasioned by the depreciation of paper money; if Franklin would subscribe his name to it, its success would be assured.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Sarah. London
    Introducing Mr. and Mrs. Bird.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 September 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Filangieri, Charlotte. Naples
    Announcing the death of her husband, Chevalier Gaetano Filangieri; his great work remains unfinished; promises to send a selection of his writings.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 359; Bigelow, X, 7).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 September 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Skinner, Richard Cortlandt. Philadelphia
    Lost his hereditary patrimony; since then studied dentition with the celebrated Dr. [Barth.] Ruspini of London; desires to practice his profession in Philadelphia; begs for the loan of the trifling sum of twenty dollars.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Greatly concerned at his illness. Often read with pleasure the papers Franklin sent him on the common conduct in life. Types and letters forwarded by Mr. John Wright.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 10; A.L.S. 5p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Hopes he has recoved from the bad attack of gout. Affairs in France; depleted state of the treasury; resignations and appointments; the States-General announced for January 1789; second meeting of the Assemblé des Notables to discuss the best way of convoking it. Urging Franklin to work on his memoirs. The country inundated with political pamphlets and memoirs; no work to compare with [Comte] de Mirabeau's on the Prussian Monarchy; fear of a famine in France.